ILGWU Murray Gross Papers 5780/199
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Murray Gross Papers
1945-1982
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Gross, Murray
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/199
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
This collection contains the papers of Murray Gross, including correspondence, newspaper clippings and other printed material.
7128068
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, May 17, 2011
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 16, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
Murray Gross entered the garment industry as a capmaker in 1925, and later worked as a tucker and a dress operator. A former student at the Brookwood Labor College, Gross was elected to the executive board of the Dress Joint Board in 1932. He was longtime manager of Local 6. In 1941, he helped found the Union for Democratic Action (later Americans for Democratic Action). After serving in the Army from 1943 to 1945, Gross served as assistant general manager of the Dress Joint Board. In 1961, he was appointed National Chairman of the American Veterans Committee, and in 1962, he was named Commission of Human Rights for the City of New York. Murray Gross passed away on July 12, 1981, in New York City.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/199 P: ILGWU Murray Gross Photographs 5780/199 AV: ILGWU Murray Gross Audio-Visual Materials 5780/199 MB: ILGWU Murray Gross Memorabilia
Women's clothing industry -- United States; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Clothing workers -- United States; Industrial relations -- United States; Gross, Maurice; American Veterans Committee
7128068
- American Veterans Committee, 1956-1971 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Business cards (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Certificate of appreciation from John V. Lindsay, 1972; letter from Ted Kennedy, 1968, 1968-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Committees, 1955-1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Scope and Contents
  Committees on which Murray Gross served
- Congratulatory letters, 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1958-1981 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Data regarding wage increase, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Murray Gross's diploma from SUNY-Empire State College, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Deborah Heart and Lung Center Testimonial Dinner Honoring Murray Gross, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- East Africa, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Death certificate of Fanny Gross, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letters of condolence, obituaries for Murray Gross, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Miscellany, 1963-1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Occasional Papers, Labor College, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Include "A decade of labor leadership, excitement, education and frustration," by Murray Gross
- ORT, Garment Employers' Chapter honors Alex Redein, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Roosevelt Day, Americans for Democratic Action, 1949-1954 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Programs
- 85th birthday tribute to George Meany, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Unity House fliers, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Clippings, 1956-1982 (Box 1, Folder 20)